Welcome back to A push in under three
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. The stage is set. America's on
the brink of collapse. The north and the
south are done with compromises.
Sectional tensions are at an all-time
high and now there's a presidential
election that's about to decide the fate
of the entire nation. America was so
divided at this point that four
different candidates ran for president.
First we have Abraham Lincoln for the
Republican Party. He was against slavery
spreading westward but not planning to
abolish it in the south. Next you have
Stephen Douglas who was a northern
Democrat. His idea was to leave
decisions in the hand of the people to
vote for. Then we had John C.
Breckenridge who was a southern
Democrat. He was very pro-slavery
wanting it everywhere. And finally we
have John Bell with a Constitutional
Union Party who pleaded for the
constitution who cares. But the real
issue Lincoln's Republican Party was
based entirely in the north and he
wasn't even on the ballot in 10 southern
states. But guess what? It didn't even
matter. He won anyway. The moment
Lincoln won the south absolutely lost
its mind. They saw it as the beginning
of the end for slavery. South Carolina
didn't wait around. It seceded just
weeks after the election. By early 1861
six more states followed forming the
Confederate States of America with
Jefferson Davis as their president.
Lincoln ran on a campaign that had at
its forefront to keep the union
together. He promised not to invade the
south unless it was necessary to fulfill
that. In April the Confederates decided
to enact the final straw and fired at
Fort Sumter a US military base in South
Carolina. Lincoln called for troops to
put down the rebellion and just like
that civil war had begun. On the screen
now are some AP style questions for this
topic. Pause now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.